Are you a person who go for long drive only
occasionally and use your car all other time
within city? Is your kilometer usage very
less? Then why are paying high premium on
your car insurance when your usage is less?
You can now pay less premium on your car insurance
if your kilometers driven is less. You can
do this with 'Pay As You Use' car insurance
policy which is introduced now in India. In
this video, I will explain how to reduce your
car insurance costs every year using this
new type of car insurance called 'Pay As You
Use' or 'Pay As You Go'.
Welcome to Save and Invest Smartly!
The 'Pay As You Use' car insurance is a part of
the sandbox initiative, where insurers can
experiment and test innovative financial products.
The sandbox approach gives an opportunity
to experiment and learn about new technology
and product, before it’s finally adopted
and offered to larger set of people. The insurance
company that has rolled out 'Pay As You Use'
car insurance policy is ICICI Lombard General
Insurance.
What is Pay As You Use Car Insurance policy?
This is a new type of car insurance where
the premium is calculated based how much distance
you drive your car. For an insurance company,
if the car is driven for lesser kilometers,
then the risk is accordingly lesser. Hence
they are ready to give a discount for such
users. The premiums are charged as per the
distance in kilometers.
How is the Sum Insured calculated?
Every vehicle has an IDV - Insured Declared Value
fixed by the insurer based on the brand,
model and age of the vehicle. It may be approximately
equivalent to the market value of the vehicle.
For example, let us consider you own a
car. There will be a market value for your
car as per the model, age of the car, etc.
IDV is approximately equivalent to the market
value.
Hence if the market value of your car
is 500000, then the sum insured that you will
get on the insurance is Rs. 500000.
How is the insurance premium calculated?
Insurance premium for a sum insured is
based on the Kilometers Plan that you select.
You may select for example 3000, 5000
or 7500 Km as the distance to be covered based
on your usage expectation. The premium will
be fixed as per your selected kilometers plan.
So if you think you will only drive 3000
Km in a year, then you may select the plan
accordingly and the insurance premium will
be far lesser than the regular premium. But
you will get the same sum assured as per the IDV
What are the Coverage Options that are available?
You may choose any of the 2 coverage options
available.
Option 1: Stand Alone Own Damage Cover
Own Damage Insuranceis a customized motorinsurancepolicy
designed to protect you and your insured vehicle
from yourown damages. That is, this policy
covers against any loss or damage to your
vehicle or its accessories due to:
1. Fire, explosion, self-ignition, accidental
damage
2. Transit, that is when the vehicle is shifted
from one place to another
3. Natural disasters like earthquake, flood,
cyclone, etc.
4. Burglary, theft, riot, etc.,
Option 2: Own Damage with Third Party
This option covers everything in Option 1
plus the third party coverage.
Third party policycovers theinsuredagainst
any legal liability arising out towards third
parties due to accidental injury or death
of a person and any damage caused to third
party property.
Lets see the Advantages of 'Pay As You Use'
Insurance policy
You will Pay low premiums if your usage
is less. That is if you drive for only few
kilometers in a year, then you pay far lesser
premium amount than the regular car insurance.
A Free telematics device is provided to
you to track your car's health and your driving
patterns. The insurance company will help
in installing this telematics device to your car.
A telematics mobile app can be installed
in your mobile, so that you can track your
car's health, kilometers used up in the plan
and also you have options to top up, etc.
If you exceed the kilometers selected,
then you can easily topup by paying additional
premium again for whatever kilometers you select.
The telematics device also sends data
to your insurer so that they can send reminders
when top up is required.
How to apply for 'Pay As You Use' policy?
If you want to get the insurance from ICICI
Lombard General Insurance,
visit www.icicilombard.com. You will see
various menu options.
Click on Products and then select the
option "Pay As You Use".
You will get a form to fill up your name,
mobile number and email id. Fill up the details
and select the Kilometers plan from the drop
down. This is to arrive at the premium for
you based on your usage.
Now tick the check box to agree the terms
and conditions. Click on Proceed.
This will take you to the next page. From
the first drop down, select the make and model
of the car.
From the next drop down select the year
of registration of the car and from the third
drop down select the city where the car is
registered. Click on 'Submit'.
The insurance agent will contact you to
get further details from you and proceed with
the documentation.
The 'Pay As You Use' policy will definitely
save you a lot of money on your car insurance
if your usage is less. Give it a try when
you apply or renew your car insurance next
time. Let me know your thoughts on this new
policy type in the comments section. Also,
write down if you have more queries on this.
Hope this video was helpful to you! Subscribe
and hit the bell icon to watch more such videos.
Give a thumbs up if you like the video. Thank
you!